
Speaker 1  (04:10)
Hello How are you lying about that? Thank you very much. As I'm afraid. 

Speaker 1  (04:18)
Open perfect, perfect. So I just sent you an email thought. I'm gonna be used with forgot about that. 

Speaker 1  (04:23)
So that's fantastic that you could join anything. Yeah? Next time. 

Speaker 1  (04:28)
Uh, so I know your schedule is busy, so let me just get into this appropriate. Okay, power effect, perfect. So again, my name is mako, kiesrie, I'm doing my PhD at our housing university Canada right now, around 2 years ago, we were working with a company that we came up with an idea to build an an ecosystem throughout the additive manufacturer. 

Speaker 1  (04:49)
Recently, I got accepted in the program. Its Denning is laptop market from Memorial University. And this program we have to talk with at least 100 people expressed like you in order to get some ideas related to our some kind of I can say raw work because it's not startup right now, we just validating for the customer discovered plan. 

Speaker 1  (05:10)
So before starting this meeting, would that be okay? If we just introduce yourself a little bit, I mean, I know everything from your late. Theme? 

Speaker 1  (05:15)
But that would be fantastic if I heard from yourself. Yeah 

Speaker 2  (05:19)
If you're recording this or not just for my now. 

Speaker 1  (05:23)
I mean, I'm trying to taking notes 

Speaker 2  (05:26)
That's fine pocket. So we have my name's Jens. Kroger, I'm Oceano begin. 

Speaker 2  (05:34)
My schooling is in physics, so I had a bachelor's, and then masters and PhD in physics. I got my PhD in 2009 and then I tried the college teaching for a semester but I didn't really like it so much. Then, did a quick postdoc at an academia. 

Speaker 2  (05:58)
But again, I don't know, didn't really feel it. So and I had the chance to obtain What existed at the time? It's called a postdoctoral industrial fellowship. 

Speaker 2  (06:13)
I think for men, the program doesn't exist anymore. I fear. But anyway, I got kind of recruited into a startup called Raymore at the time and in the field of plasma science for material synthesis. 

Speaker 2  (06:28)
Alright, so these are high temperature. Set a high temperature processes. Like, you know, a few 1000°C, and the idea was to synthesize a nanocarbon particles for various applications. 

Speaker 2  (06:45)
I did that for 9 years. All the way to the director of technology at that startup, and then I gotta know notice that the startup world is really It's difficult and you need a ton of patience and You know, it didn't really Yeah, the world of materials is a really good Difficult world like the road from discovering a new material such as carbon Nano nanoparticles to application and qualification. Is I think it takes decades in all honesty? 

Speaker 2  (07:24)
And yeah, I didn't really at that time. I didn't really have the patience anymore to watch and wait, so I decided to apply at larger company. And I joined the company and now work in 2019 and it's called apnc. 

Speaker 2  (07:41)
And it's part of GE aerospace and BHP. Equilibrium additive, so that it's like an onion. So the big mother company's gro space, and underneath that there's What we call propulsion, and then there's G Equilibrium additive, and then there's us ap and C and we make mostly titanium, but also nickel powders our additive manufacturing. 

Speaker 1  (08:08)
It's accent, thank you very much. That was fantastic. So before talking about the idea, I mean, the procedure is like this. 

Speaker 1  (08:15)
I do have a couple of questions, just 4 or 5 questions, and I would ask each person, and I really would like the honest and brutal answer. And we have to say, brutal, this is important, and at the end of that I will talk more in detail about what is my idea. Would that be okay with you? 

Speaker 1  (08:29)
If you just go through that precision fantastic, I mean, sorry. I have to read it from some kind of my computer. Some of the questions a little bit long, so my first question would be about the rnd to production theory risking could you walk me through the ap and C not detail? 

Speaker 1  (08:48)
But the whole process for derising a technology from initial concept through full production qualification. What are the critical stage gates and decision points that you have throughout this process? 

Speaker 2  (09:03)
The question it depends a lot on the scale of the project, so we carry out very small projects and in very large projects. So for the small ones again, we kind of differentiate between trials that we can do in an rnd environment and those that we do in a production environment. And if we do proceed in a production environment, let's say for new sensor or new Improve production method. 

Speaker 2  (09:35)
We have to go through Documentation due to ukra. All to prevent kind of a little risk analysis to mitigate the risks in the production environment and in the risks that are applied to our product, right? Because we would need these new improvements or I would would then be would have an impact on our product. 

Speaker 2  (10:04)
And yeah, in general, we try to obviously to, you know, to define Ah, I'm climbing and validate, so validation is maybe the most important part of the small projects were we. Again, that ideally at the outset, there's There's a validation plan of things to verify before they can be implemented a production environment. So it's like the, you know, the scientific method where you have a hypothesis. 

Speaker 2  (10:38)
And then you support our invalidate. So it's really like that. Maybe in a more formal way, with a list of criteria to validate and a method to validate and sometimes a frequency, a sampling frequency, things like that, to be the idea is for you to do that in a pretty strict way. 

Speaker 1  (11:01)
I'm so sorry for thank you. Which leads to my talk? I've got a second questions is about material gaps. 

Speaker 1  (11:09)
So from your materials expertise, what are the most significant gaps in standardized materials characterization for additive manufacturing, where does redundant testing happen? And what does that cost? 

Speaker 2  (11:28)
So you're talking additive manufacturing, which is additive, so I don't really know the plastic space that much. So I can only talk to the theater. The metal's space has been specifically. 

Speaker 2  (11:41)
I can only talk about the powders. And one thing that is still difficult to assess today is Is the reality of a metal powder? And its behavior in a printer So there's there's very many, many, many tests to determine some parameters, but most of those are not very repeatable. 

Speaker 2  (12:07)
So powder powder, reallogy depends on the environment humidity. Static electricity, but also powder properties such size morphology. So there's a million things that have an impact, but also the measurement instrument itself, sometimes even the In the way that the technicians will handle the equipment, so it's very difficult. 

Speaker 2  (12:32)
And today we use like funnels and we time the time we time many seconds. It takes for our specific weight of powder to flow through a funnel, but it's It's a pre arcade, a pretty simple method. So it has quite a few limits. 

Speaker 2  (12:49)
I think that's one of the main Problems, especially for less dense metals such as aluminum or titanium. 

Speaker 1  (12:58)
Make saint sense. So I'm gonna ask a question, Eric is actually out of my questions. What are you talking with the industry? 

Speaker 1  (13:05)
I mean, so far I talk with more than maybe 50 people from different kind of industries, one of the reasons that somehow there are a little bit conservative? Again? Using am is that they don't trust. 

Speaker 1  (13:18)
I mean the way that this scene, the am or additive manufacturing are talk about the metal side. Okay, metal is important for me, because my main focus is about oil and gas industries and offshore locations. So they prefer to have that big, big and massive warehouse rather than maybe try to trust additive manufacturing only for a smart port, a very small portion. 

Speaker 1  (13:41)
What do you think the reason for that? The main reason for that is right now from your perspective. 

Speaker 2  (13:49)
There's still a lot of costs, still quite expensive at a different manufacturing, and it's still something that And it is there's a lot of complications, and there's a lot of subtleties and yeah, it takes groups that have very specific use cases where the added value can really be measured. And you see that in the biomedical space, where you can print implants that really have very organic shapes, and these you cannot do using a traditional machining. So additive manufacturing, unfortunately, has kind of only been You or are you or is used really in parts that you can't make otherwise yeah. 

Speaker 2  (14:39)
At scale, you know, like today today, there's phone cases that are being printed. There's watch cases that are being printed. There's implants, there's specific aerospace parts, but everything that can be done using milling and traditional cnc machining. 

Speaker 2  (14:57)
Most of the time When you have a simple geometry, it's cheaper to make it like that. And then to 3 printed, so I think it comes down to cost and expertise. 

Speaker 1  (15:10)
Yeah, that makes sense. Yeah, like this idea. So my next question again, I'm trying to have my questions around the brisk management. 

Speaker 1  (15:18)
Because I believe that's a very important part. So in one of your posts, actually in your LinkedIn, you mentioned that addressing high risk elements first with fast pace test, so could you walk me a little bit through your risk management framework, and how do you identify prioritize and validateize risk reduction? I mean, mostly I'm talking about a and additive manufacturing kind of projects. 

Speaker 2  (15:47)
Ideally, you can separate a project into elements that have where you can identify a risk with each element. You can always do that. And sometimes there's new risks that arise when you combine these elements, but if you can isolate the risks and address the biggest ones first. 

Speaker 2  (16:06)
Right. That was a good idea to Yeah, to address these big risks rapidly kind of the fail. Fast idea, right where you do A At the beginning, it really comes down to trial-and-error right? 

Speaker 2  (16:21)
You do lots of tests, and you'll learn a lot. And you mitigate a lot of risks. And then, as you gain In assurance that it's going to work and The credibility of a project rises. 

Speaker 2  (16:36)
Then, you can Spend more money or more resources and plan out for longer time spanning it. But there should always be like a really an rnd phase for something that's an innovation, or you just Test the basic concept and test it fast and test many different options. Because if you don't do that and you start planning out big budgets, big projects, big things with big teams. 

Speaker 2  (17:07)
You're probably going to run into a lot of problems. 

Speaker 1  (17:10)
I agree. Perfect. My next question is about documentation. 

Speaker 1  (17:15)
I mean, as you just mentioned about that. When you trans, you have a transition, a validated design from rnt to production, what kind of metadata. And documentations must transfer Verde's information loss happen, and what does reverse cost? 

Speaker 1  (17:32)
Introduction. 

Speaker 2  (17:35)
There's lots of during those transition, you can lose a lot of information. So I mean, we have a so we have a quality system. At a pnc, so every time you work, I mean many, many industries, right? 

Speaker 2  (17:49)
They have the iPhone 9001. Quality quality system, but we have other certifications related to the fact that we work in regulated industries such as biomedical and aerospace. So we have additional requirements that we have to do, and these are right now. 

Speaker 2  (18:09)
Concern, for example, you know, a critical so we have identified critical That critical components, critical parameters that need to be satisfied and need to be correct for the system to work. So when we're going to transition a big rmb project, we need Ideally, you know, we have. We have different risk analysis that we have done beforehand so these would be such as a security risk for the operators, a product risk analysis A design risk analysis so they're followed So it's something that the NASA invented back in the days when they launched rockets. 

Speaker 2  (18:52)
It's called pfmea or dfmea. So failure mode effects analysis. So those are the types of analysis that we're going to do, you know you want to add a good R&D report? 

Speaker 2  (19:04)
And then From Lee, we're gonna start the A real engineering project before we put something into production with further validation and General validation plan, this is going to have many steps. And then we're going to include all the other stakeholders in the company, the qualities people, the supply people. The logistics people, the production people and make sure that all of them can voice there You know there's things that are Their fears and their loved one Uncertainties, and there are questions about the The new innovation that we're going to try to put into production. 

Speaker 2  (19:47)
So usually that comes what results from that is a long plan that we're going to need to follow through before we can then qualify in equipment. And that's also, there's going to be a qualification phase that's quite generic. It's called IQ oq pq. 

Speaker 2  (20:05)
So IQ stands for installation qualification, then oq, for like operation qualification, like the first run so to speak. And then pq, the production qualification. So that's, you know, the innovation or just the new equipment work. 

Speaker 2  (20:22)
Many, many times over So yeah, there's there's we have a very structured way of putting new things into production. That's I'll prescribe by our quality system But we still can lose information, right. If the people that design the equipment and it's I kind of had the strategy and the sequence in their head, and it's not documented. 

Speaker 2  (20:49)
Or if the people that do the control they go into a different direction and have lots of complexity, and you can mess up, right? Or you can Lester, budget or Buster delivery timeline, or something? So what happens frequently? 

Speaker 1  (21:08)
So perfect. You mentioned something about the prescribed qualification process. So this is this question is after the questions that they have, because I also heard about that. 

Speaker 1  (21:21)
Imagine that you are an industry and you have the 3-D printer, and you would like to produce a part, not critical apart again. The part is not that liquidity, that be huge. But as long as it's going to solve a temper, it's going to be considered a temporary solution. 

Speaker 1  (21:39)
This prescribed quality assurance. Do you think it's possible for industries to have that? I mean, or no, they need still need to have all of those labs and all of those tests to make sure that a product is going to be okay. 

Speaker 1  (21:56)
And consider a certified, somehow 

Speaker 2  (22:01)
It's a tricky question. I mean, somebody from I mean, it really depends on the application rate. So what you're saying is essentially, when you qualify a prototype. 

Speaker 2  (22:16)
Without going through all the tests. Well, it's a case-by-case situation. And somebody needs to assess the risk, right? 

Speaker 2  (22:26)
So does it? Is it something that's going to be directly go to consumer? I suppose not right it's going to be used in another company right for them to make something. 

Speaker 2  (22:39)
So what is that process is it like? Is it a medical company? That's making a serum for blood. 

Speaker 2  (22:47)
Well then, maybe you know the new part. Is it directly in contact with the product? If yes, then that's at much higher risk than if it's just Doing, I don't know supporting like some some book, a bookcase or something. 

Speaker 2  (23:01)
And that's that's how you want to introduce new technologies. Like am so in the aerospace, they started with brackets, right? Things that were much less sensitive than rotating components in an engine 

Speaker 1  (23:16)
Yes, exactly. I mean, so yeah? 

Speaker 2  (23:20)
Don't depend thither, and in a real expert was all is always gonna answer. It depends that's the expert answer to any question. 

Speaker 1  (23:29)
That makes sense. And about the aerospace, I mean, I talk to 2 companies, Galaxy and reaction dynamics. I mean, they are already using 3D printers. 

Speaker 1  (23:40)
I mean they're working on that, but I still have to talk in detail with them, to have their perspective to what's going on. And final question is about scaling, because this is one of the important things that I heard a lot about scaling, and also in one of your posts, you mentioned that combining old and new technology, from metalogy and additive manufacturing to machine vision and machine learning. And we all like that a lot, so what does that look like? 

Speaker 1  (24:10)
In practice, and what problems are you trying to solve at scale? What's the cost of implementation? I'm talking about the machine learning vision system. 

Speaker 1  (24:20)
The reason I'm focusing on that is that I'm working in my PhD. I'm working on AI and machine learning. So I really would like to know you her idea about using this kind of new technologies in am industries. 

Speaker 2  (24:35)
I mean, I think it's more A I think that the key is to identify specific use cases were Um, where you can understand the risk of it going wrong, right? So Can you look at you? I mean, for me, translation rate was the first kind of application of it. 

Speaker 2  (25:03)
I've large language models by Google Translate. Great. But I had no risk. 

Speaker 2  (25:08)
Right? If it gave up c***, you know, people would just, oh that's c***, I'm not, you know. You shouldn't rate your PhD thesis with the machine learning algorithm of 20 years ago. 

Speaker 2  (25:21)
Now, maybe you could probably translate from English to French with machine learning, and it would be mostly. Okay, yeah So if you use like, I don't know vision. So that is stuff that we use in our company. 

Speaker 2  (25:35)
We use better vision algorithms to protect features. And So you have to always. I mean, obviously it is faster and better than other algorithms. 

Speaker 2  (25:46)
I think we all agree on that. But we have to be aware of what happens if it detects some like a false, positive or a false negative You know, we have to be aware of that. And if we can Now tolerate those mistakes, and it's fine. 

Speaker 2  (26:02)
When it's a good idea to move ahead, and I think that's the same. And what we do is obviously we have human verification after many years. Have predictions, not the right word, but recommendations by algorithms right since 

Speaker 1  (26:20)
I think it's taken recently. The human yet we cannot trust AI. That's much so perfect. 

Speaker 1  (26:25)
Thank you very much. I mean I love it by questions. So let me talk a little bit about my idea. 

Speaker 1  (26:30)
It's not physics idea right now. So as I just mentioned, we would like to focus on ecosystems, the ecosystem between different entities by entities. I mean, the end user clients, the oems, three different printing facilities and some kind of certification and regulation bodies like dnv and Lloyd. 

Speaker 1  (26:48)
So the idea was that encouraging industries to install 3D printers on sites in order to produce some parts again, non critical parts, not that kind of very maybe rotating or reported parts that they need lots of lots of regulations and timing just in case for the time they need to fix something. Because, as you know, if you're talking about maybe 500 or a $100 material, or maybe the part we are not only talking about debt, we are talking about million dollars of the gustories. That is that is shutting down because of that. 

Speaker 1  (27:22)
The specific thing they have to wait for the ship and they have to wait for everything so beside that. Obviously we cannot say additive manufacturing. If you don't talk about digital inventory. 

Speaker 1  (27:33)
So we also thought about helping industries to maybe invest a little on digital inventory rather than just having those massive warehouse. Maybe there are so many parts obsolete parts, they do have so much problem with that. Try to put it inside this some kind of platform. 

Speaker 1  (27:49)
Obviously takes a lot of time. It takes a lot of effort because you have to deal with regulations. You have to deal with end users, and most importantly, you have to deal with some kind of policy platform. 

Speaker 1  (28:00)
Everything should be connected, secure and everything should happen like that. So I would like to know your idea about the whole concept of digital inventory and do you think this kind of platforms are going to be a good solution for oil and gas industry. There isn't I'm trying to specif why that the oil and gas is that I know they are doing it in health as you just mentioned like a company named polyunity, they are already doing this concept somehow and Europe, and also the US they also doing the same concept, but in Canada, we have a name with field note they're working with Equinox. 

Speaker 1  (28:40)
So they're working on that, but again, our idea is going to be a little bit more broad, it's not going to be just specific like that. But I really would like to know your idea about this kind of platform we think it's early or we think we have some kind of It's special in Canada, wise. 

Speaker 2  (29:01)
And so you're targeting, like Multiple companies with one platform 

Speaker 1  (29:07)
The oil and gas 

Speaker 2  (29:10)
And in the tricky part is that companies don't like to share their secrets, right? Yes. 

Speaker 1  (29:14)
That's the ID. Yeah, that's the thing. 

Speaker 2  (29:18)
Hey, there really are a very, very Risk-averse in terms of like sharing their suppliers given a supplier, even if it shouldn't be secret. Companies really don't like to share that kind of stuff like, you know how many boats and how many? How many bolts and nuts are they using per year? 

Speaker 2  (29:37)
How many valves? What type of valves It sounds it sounds ridiculous, but traditionally, these companies don't like to share this type of information with any type of public service. So it's almost a game of politics. 

Speaker 2  (29:59)
How are you going to convince these companies to share all this information and to kind of work in A Open collaborative way, I mean there's right. If you look on the internet you're going to find a billion open collaboration platforms about all topics from AI to am to whatnot like nanosensors and blah blah blah. But in reality, got like private companies, really don't kind of don't really like that stuff too much. 

Speaker 2  (30:31)
So we're gonna sometimes fund these things if they're very early stage You know, like I have no time to spend on this. Go ahead, just like. But if it becomes any like really sensitive, and it is critical to their growth and their competitiveness, then usually they're going to restrain from going in a collaborative way. 

Speaker 2  (30:52)
Yeah, I mean Tom. There's this gap between universities and Private companies that is, we all would like to work more collaboratively together, but But that IP thing is, is the biggest hurdle, and for the time being. I don't see a significant change. 

Speaker 2  (31:11)
I don't see a big pressure enough from the economy to open up those gates. It doesn't mean it can't be done. It doesn't mean it's a bad idea. 

Speaker 2  (31:22)
But it's maybe the biggest hurdles that I see the biggest hurdle 

Speaker 1  (31:27)
Yeah, that completely makes sense. I mean, throughout this kind of the customer discovery, I mean, we were talking with so many some kind of industries, one of the industries that showed interest somehow was about the defense and navy. I mean, I talked with some people from thalas air venture building. 

Speaker 1  (31:46)
There are looking for new technologies, especially each year. There's some kind of budget is increasing. Yet we still have to find a way to go through their rnd. 

Speaker 1  (31:54)
I mean, I found out the Canada would like to have this kind of not. Maybe this platform exactly, but I really would like to have the very secure platform for itself, especially after the COVID happened. And all of those supply chain, it understand that they cannot rely all the time on China or Europe. 

Speaker 1  (32:13)
They have to do something about it. But, yeah, I mean that was fantastic. I really would like to know the brutal and something of the honest answer because some 

Speaker 2  (32:20)
No, but I mean, if you if you build some platform, and then you can I mean, obviously the military would be a good entry. Climb right, and they would kind of just study the thing. And if then it became really critical, they would probably want to onboard it and then make it like not private. 

Speaker 2  (32:41)
But make it like Not public anymore, right, so He said, well, yeah, there's definitely a desire by I own militaries in the world to be doing To diminish their dependence on the long supply chain. So the problem that you're identified is a real problem, it's a good problem to work on. And But there's yeah, there's so many hurdles that Finding the right. 

Speaker 2  (33:12)
Kind of? Like to any business, right? The challenge is already always defined the right. 

Speaker 2  (33:18)
First customer, if you can find that you're good to go for like 10 20 30 years and maybe growing or whatever, but you can find that the right fit for your first customer and you're not going to go anywhere, yeah 

Speaker 1  (33:34)
Complacent, oh, that's what we are trying to do I mean right now, I'm one man Army, but I'm trying to assume, maybe build a team to work on that because yeah, as you just mentioned we have to find This Way. But anyways, thank you very much. It just passed the time and I really appreciate it one last favor I mean at the end of each meeting I do have that so right now as you can see, I'm gathering knowledge. 

Speaker 1  (33:56)
I'm trying to learn and learn maybe in future. Maybe a couple of months I said that, hey, do you have another maybe 1520 minutes of talk that I can share some knowledge with you sit at yeah, I completely found out. This idea is complete mess or maybe I found out no I have a customer so do I have that permission? 

Speaker 1  (34:12)
Is that okay with you? 

Speaker 2  (34:14)
Yeah, of course. Of course, perfect. That's fantastic. 

Speaker 2  (34:16)
Hey, good luck. Yeah, good luck with your endeavor and don't give up even if it looks grim. If you believe in it, don't give up, yeah. 

Speaker 1  (34:25)
Really appreciate? Thank you very much episode 8. Thank you. 
